Finding Aid for Nathaniel A. Balch papers, 1797-1884
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nathaniel A. Balch papers 1797-1884
Balch, Nathaniel A. (Nathaniel Aldrich), 1808-1894.
1 linear foot and 1 oversize folder
85905 Aa 2 Ac
Kalamazoo, Michigan, educator, Democratic state senator. Correspondence, legal papers, genealogical data, diaries and account books; and compositions concerning Kalamazoo College, Middlebury College, Zebulon Pike, James W. Ransom, temperance, the Presbyterian church of Kalamazoo, and Marshall Academy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Gertrude den Bleyker (donor no. 378 ) and came to the library in 1938.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Nathaniel A. Balch was born at Athens, Vt., Jan. 22, 1808. He graduated from Middlebury College and then took the position of principal of an academy in Bennington, Vt. In 1837 he came to Kalamazoo and opened and organized the Kalamazoo Literary Institute, the institution that would become Kalamazoo College. While in Kalamazoo, Balch resumed the study of law which he had begun in Vermont. He was admitted to the practice of law in 1840. He served as prosecuting attorney for Barry County in 1840 and for Kalamazoo County in 1841. He served in the Michigan State Senate for the Fifth District for one term, 1847-1848. In 1860 he was the Democratic nominee for Congress but was defeated. Balch died Feb. 1, 1894.
The collection includes family letters of the Balch and Dungan families, with one letter (1813) reporting on the death and burial of General Zebulon Pike. There are some legal and business papers, some private and some connected with Kalamazoo College. The diaries are incomplete with brief entries. The volumes were also used for legal notes and business accounts. Other papers include manuscripts (1834-35) during Balch's stay at Middlebury College; addresses on temperance, education, and other subjects; and miscellaneous post office and county records. There are some papers of Balch's son while a student at The University of Michigan (1865-66).
Subjects:
First Presbyterian Church (Kalamazoo, Mich.: 1836-1842); Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kalamazoo College.; Marshall College (Marshall, Mich.); Middlebury College.; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Ransom, James W.; Temperance--Michigan--Kalamazoo.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Personal papers
  - Correspondence, 1848-1882 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical data on the Balch family (Box 1)
  - Compositions and addresses while a student at Middlebury college, 1832-1835 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions on Balch death (Box 1)
  - Papers relating to the family of Elizabeth Ewing (Box 1)
  - Dungan Balch, 1797-1848 (Box 1)
  - Obituary of James W. Ransom (Box 1)
  - Pledge taken by pastor and elders of the Presbyterian Church of Kalamazoo (Box 1)
  - Compositions by Balch on farewell to his students, and compositions by his students (Box 1)
  - Poems (Box 1)
  - Handwritten booklets on Marshall Academy, 1838 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers
    - 1838-1861 (Box 1)
    - 1862-1862 (Box 1)
    - 1871-1883 (Box 1)
  - Compositions and addresses, including several on temperance, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Receipts, etc., 1847-1948, from Kalamazoo County Agricultural Society (Box 1)
  - Diaries and account books, 1852-1884, 21 volumes in box (Box 1)
  - Deeds, indentures and mortgages (Folder 1)